Guide to the Consumer Reports. Robert L. Smith papers RL.11861
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports. Robert L. Smith papers
1938-1978
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports (Firm)
RL.11861
8.0 Linear Feet
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Robert L. Smith was a consumer advocate who served as Assistant Director of Consumers Union from 1963-1971. The Robert L. Smith papers largely span Smith's tenure as Assistant Director of Consumers Union, along with files he inherited from predecessors and some materials filed under his name after Smith's death in 1971. The collection includes correspondence, meeting minutes, grant applications and other records, materials relating to state and regional consumer organizations, records of educational and social outreach programs, permissions to reprint Consumer Reports content, and other printed materials. In addition the collection includes records pertaining to a Consumers Union study performed for the U.S. Defense Department on consumer protections for military personnel. Correspondents include Colston Warne, Esther Peterson, Irving Michelson and Walter Sandbach. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Administrative and Office Files; Department of Defense Study Materials
Biographical / Historical
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Robert L. Smith was a consumer advocate who served as Assistant Director of Consumers Union from 1963-1971. Smith was born in 1912. He graduated from Amherst College (BA, Economics, 1934) and served with a number of consumer cooperative associations: Eastern Cooperatives (1934-1948); Cooperative Consumers of New Haven (1948-1952); Palo Alto Consumers Cooperative Society (1952-1963). Smith joined Consumers Union as Assistant Director in 1963 and served until his death in 1971.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Consumer Reports. Robert L. Smith papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Consumer Reports Archives records
Consumer Reports. Colston E. Warne papers
Consumer Reports. Esther Peterson papers
Collection Overview
The Robert L. Smith papers largely span Smith's tenure as Assistant Director of Consumers Union, along with files he inherited from predecessors and some materials filed under his name after Smith's death in 1971. The collection includes correspondence, meeting minutes, grant applications and other records, materials relating to state and regional consumer organizations, records of educational and social outreach programs, permissions to reprint Consumer Reports content, and other printed materials. In addition the collection includes records pertaining to a Consumers Union study performed for the U.S. Defense Department on consumer protections for military personnel. Correspondents include Colston Warne, Esther Peterson, Irving Michelson and Walter Sandbach.
Consumer education; Consumer advocacy; consumer protection; Smith, Robert L.; United States. Department of Defense; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
- Administrative and Office Files, 1938-1978; 1
  - Aims, scope and function of Consumers Union, 1963-1971 (Box 1)
  - Annual meeting, 1965-1971; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Biographical, obituary, etc., 1938-1971; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors memos, 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - Consumer movement, 1963-1971 (Box 2)
  - Consumer organizations by state, Alaska-New York, 1963-1971; 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Consumer protection, 1966-1971 (Box 2)
  - Consumers Union reputation: Honesty, integrity, 1963-1971; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Consumers Union tax status, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1969; 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1971; 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--Esther Peterson, David Swankin, 1964-1972 (Box 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Esther Peterson was the President Lyndon Johnson's advisor on consumer affairs; David Swankin was Director of the U.S. Bureau of Labor Standards
  - Education and Grants Committee, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Education and Grants Committee, 1962-1968; 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Education and Grants Committee, 1968-1970; 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Educational broadcasting, 1962-1970 (Box 6)
  - Grants, 1959-1961; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Grants, 1961-1964; 8 folders (Box 7)
  - Grants, 1965-1969; 8 folders (Box 8)
  - Grants, 1969-1971; 7 folderss (Box 9)
  - Grants, 1971-1978; 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Local group relations, 1964-1971 (Box 10)
  - Permissions to reprint, 1963 (Box 10)
  - Permissions to reprint, 1964-1968; 8 folders (Box 11)
  - Permissions to reprint, 1968-1972; 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Policy, 1967-1971; 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Reports on Consumers Union, 1964-1970 (Box 12)
  - Tarrytown meeting, 1971 (Box 12)
    Board of Directors' retreat and meeting
- Department of Defense Study, 1968-1969; 2
  - Budgets, publicity, 1968-1969 (Box 13)
  - Consultants, contacts, personnel involved, 1968-1969; 5 folders (Box 13)
    Includes Frederick McLaughlin, Henry Munn, Leslie Dix, Irett Ferris, Irving Michelson, Robert Doland, William Hyde
  - General, 1968-1969 (Box 13)
  - Interim report, 1968 (Box 13)
  - Price information, 1968-1969 (Box 14)
  - Price information, 1968-1969 (Box 15)
  - Publicity, 1968-1969 (Box 15)
  - Report, Consumer Protection Study, 1969; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Visits to bases and Department of Defense, 1968-1969 (Box 14)